Previously on
Battlestar Galactica.
We haven't been properly
introduced. I'm Leoben.
I'm looking forward to spending a
little more time with you, Starbuck.
We have a lot to talk about!
It's gonna be fun.
Congratulations, Commander.
The Pegasus is your command.
Hey, I am picking up
a large planetary body.
It's habitable. We may have just found
a world that can support human life.
I know in my gut that
settling on this planet's
gonna mean disaster
for humanity,
and I will not say otherwise
just to win an election.
I take the office of President
of the 12 Colonies of Kobol.
And I am going to sign
my first executive order
requiring to immediately
establish settlements
on the planet we have come
to know as New Caprica.
If you want to move down
there, go ahead, be my guest.
Go down and cat around
with all the men.
Saul, I want you.
At last, a safe haven
we can call home.
Oh, my Gods!
The Cylon fleet, they found us.
We have to get out
of here, sir.
We can't just leave
all those people behind.
There's nothing we can do.
We're in no shape
for a fight, sir.
They'll be wiped out.
We don't have a choice.
We need to get out
of here right now!
Begin jump prep. We're leaving.
But we'll be back.
The Cylons just
jumped into orbit.
And the fleet's jumped away.
They've left us.
On behalf of the
people of the 12 Colonies,
I surrender.
I'm looking for Kara Thrace.
Do you know that every time
they take you out of this cell,
we come in here and we change
those little hashmarks
on your little calendar there
you're trying to hide?
Potatoes, gravy,
even some carrots.
Heavenly Father, we thank you
for the bounty of this table.
Yes.
Come on, don't stop.
Come on, come on,
you son of a bitch!
You son of a bitch!
Oh, yeah.
Oh, boy.
All right, we're armed.
They're inbound. Let's move!
I need a knife.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I must say,
I quite enjoyed that.
I'm so glad.
And when do I get what I want?
I believe that's happening
right now.
We reviewed your case today,
and I must say there was great
disappointment on the review committee.
Come on.
We've got to get you processed.
It'll take an hour or so.
Bureaucracy must be served.
But if you're lucky, you'll
get home by dinnertime.
Colonel, come on.
I'm not gonna hold
this door open forever.
Attention, New Capricans.
Effective immediately, a pot of water
will be given to residents in
even-numbered pods on even-numbered days
and odd-numbered pods on odd-numbered days.
Rationing will be...
Saul!
Oh, sweetheart.
What did they do to you?
It's all right. I'm out,
and that's all that matters.
Come on, now,
let's get out of here.
Okay.
Okay, ready? Now!
Oh, for frak sakes.
Come on! Come on!
Is that thing gonna work
or what?
It worked that time.
Come on. Go, go!
Frakking insurgents.
You look so lovely tonight.
I'll see you soon, Kara.
Take your time.
"One hundred
and thirty fourth day
"of the Cylon occupation
of New Caprica.
"Today is Mars Day.
"Somehow it seems appropriate
to honor the God of War
"on a day when it feels
like perpetual war
"is the only realistic
prospect for us.
"We've had no contact with Galactica
since it left four months ago.
"But I refuse to believe
that Adama has abandoned us.
"Our insurgency has been
striking back against the Cylons
"whenever
and wherever possible.
"Although at times, these attacks
seem like futile gestures,
"I believe that they are
critical to morale,
"to maintaining
some measure of hope.
"But in order for the insurgency
to have a more meaningful impact,
"we need to strike
a high-profile target.
"It is simply not enough to kill
Cylons, because they don't die.
"They resurrect themselves, and
they continue to walk among us.
"It is horrifying.
"The Cylon Occupation Authority
continues to exert complete control
"over the city,
and we remain at their mercy."
"The Colonial Government,
under President Gaius Baltar,"
"functions in name only."
Let's review why we're here,
shall we?
We're supposed to bring the word
of God to the people, right?
To save humanity from damnation
by bringing the love of God to
these poor benighted people.
We're here because
the majority of the Cylon
felt that the slaughter of
mankind had been a mistake.
We're here to find a new
way to live in peace,
as God wants us to live.
And it's been a fun ride
so far.
But I want to clarify
our objectives.
If we're bringing
the word of God,
then it follows
that we should employ any
means necessary to do so.
Any means. Yes.
Fear is a key article
of faith, as I understand it.
So perhaps it's time to
instill a little more fear
into the people's
hearts and minds.
Let's execute Baltar.
What, what?
That's not gonna happen.
Just because
he's your favorite toy
shouldn't be allowed to interfere
with the larger issues here.
I think that
I have cooperated...
Gaius is with me.
Anyone who wants to challenge
that will have to deal with me.
No, it doesn't matter.
If we'd killed him at the
beginning, it might have worked.
But now most humans
think of him as a traitor
and would actually
cheer his death.
Fine, fine.
We don't kill Baltar.
We round up the leaders of the insurgency,
and we execute them publicly.
We round up, at random,
groups off the street,
and we execute them publicly.
Send a message that the
gloves are coming off.
The insurgency stops now or else we
start reducing the human population
to a more manageable size.
I don't know,
say less than 1,000.
We need to stop being butchers.
The entire point of coming here
was to start a new way of life,
to push past the conflict that
separated us from humans for so long.
And what has it gotten us?
It's not like
they welcomed us with...
Oh, frak it, never mind. You're
all living in a fantasy world.
Consider the irony in that!
Delusional machines.
What's the universe
gonna come up with next?
Is it really worth it, Caprica?
Is the love of that man really
worth possibly losing all of this?
If you ever experienced love,
you wouldn't have to ask.
"In recent months, the Cylons
have been recruiting and training humans
"in an attempt to establish
a human police force.
"It is hard to think
of anything more despicable
"than humans doing the
dirty work of the Cylons.
"Led to believe they were merely
taking the civilian security
"out of the hands
of the Cylons,
"the members
of the human police
"have since become an extension of
the Cylons' corporeal authority.
"And while their names
are kept deeply confidential,"
"there's no question some of them
are people we might least expect."
”Hundreds of us have been
rounded up by the Cylons,
"held in detention,
questioned, tortured.
"Others have simply vanished.
"In recent weeks,
"we've been gaining access to
some very important documents
"from a source within
Baltar's administration.
"No one knows who this
mysterious benefactor is,
"but he communicates with the
insurgents by means of a secret signal.
"We pray every day for the men
and women who risk their lives"
"to fight the Cylons."
"They have everything to lose and such
little hope of something to gain."
Hey, Jake.
There we go.
It looks like Mommy's gonna get
some sleep tonight after all.
You know, sometimes I hate
everything about this place.
But sometimes it's magic.
I gotta go. Be back
in a couple hours.
One of these days you're just
not gonna come back, are you?
You'll just vanish,
and that'll be it.
I'll never see you again.
Nick will never know
his father.
A couple hours, promise.
Good to see you, Colonel.
It's good to be seen.
I know you're wondering,
so I'll save you the trouble.
The eye is gone.
Ripped it right out,
onto the floor,
picked it up
and showed it to me.
It looked like
a hardboiled egg.
Big boom today.
Hope that was you two.
Oh, yeah. A heavy Raider, too.
Good man.
What's our next target?
Well, we got these today.
They're security plans
for the graduation ceremony
of the New Caprica
Police Academy.
These are right out
of the Ministry files.
Where are you getting
this stuff?
Who's your source?
I have no idea. The source won't
tell me what their name is.
It's probably safer
for all of us.
We've been getting
stuff like this for weeks.
Humans working for the Cylons,
makes me wanna puke.
Yeah, well, all of the top Occupation
brass is gonna be at the graduation,
even President Baltar.
Gaius Baltar?
Yes, sir.
I think we can get
a shot at him, too.
The problem is, it's gonna be
tough avoiding human casualties.
Don't avoid them!
Send a message.
You work with the Cylons,
you're a target.
No boundaries for the Cylons,
there's no boundaries for us!
Anything we can do to nail that son of
a bitch, Gaius Baltar, is worth doing.
Where are we on the wireless?
Nowhere. Every day we try
and contact the Raptor,
and every day the Cylons
jam the transmission.
I've asked the inside source
to tell us
which of the Cylon jamming
frequencies are the weakest,
but so far I've got nothing.
You guys are dreaming. There's
no Raptor there, okay?
There hasn't been one for the
past four months, either.
Galactica's not coming back.
They're not.
Accept it. You watch
your frakking mouth!
There's a Raptor out there every day,
listening for our wireless call.
It's out there because that was
the plan if anything happened.
And it's out there because the old man
isn't just gonna leave us to the Cylons!
The old man left me
to the Cylons, Colonel.
And if it wasn't for my wife
being a royal pain in the ass
and refusing to let it go,
I would be dead a year now.
Any word on Kara?
Nothing in four months.
Hi, honey. I'm home.
You kill me, I download,
I come back, we start over.
Five times now.
I'm trying to help you, Kara.
I only want you to see
the truth of your life,
the reason why you suffered and
you struggled for so long.
That's why God sent me to you.
That's why God wants us
to be together.
You're right.
And I hear you. I do.
Okay.
So, thank you.
Thank you
for putting up with me.
I'm so sorry.
Put it down, Kara.
Just put it down.
I'm a patient man.
You're not a man.
I'm willing to wait.
You just need more time.
I don't need more frakking time.
It's never gonna happen.
Of course it's gonna happen.
You're gonna hold me in your arms.
You're gonna embrace me. You're
gonna tell me that you love me.
I've seen it.
You're insane.
To know the face of God
is to know madness.
I'm going to bed.
Be nice if you joined me.
Either way, you're spending
the night with me.
I do love you, Kara Thrace.
Good night.
Let me out!
Let me out of here!
I don't belong here!
Let me out!
Racetrack, adjust
your center line 20 degrees.
Snowbird Three,
get in formation.
Okay, Snowbirds,
let's nail this exercise.
How many times
are we gonna run this thing?
What, you're not having fun?
Come on, focus, Snowbirds!
Snowbirds, Galactica.
Regroup into deployment formation
and proceed to position one.
Snowbird One to Snowbirds,
drop point in eight seconds.
Okay, Snowbirds, let's get
this deployment bang on.
The Admiral's
watching every move.
Roger, Kat.
We go on your command.
Bomb bay doors opened.
All Vipers break.
Now, now, now!
Deploy drones on my mark.
Three, two, one, mark!
Frak me!
Gods damn it, Snowbird Four,
what the hell happened?
Can the chatter, Snowbirds.
This is the CAG.
Abort maneuver.
I say again, decoy
squadron abort maneuver.
Roger that, leader.
Snowbirds, fall back. Abort the drill.
Await further instructions.
Frak, they're on my wing.
Galactica, Kat.
It is a mess out here.
We've got decoy drones
heading every which way.
Request instructions.
Roger that, Kat.
Abort acknowledged.
You're approaching bingo fuel anyway.
Bring your birds back home.
Belay that.
Strike my last. Stand by.
Launch the tanker bird.
Let them practice their in-flight
refueling before they recover the drones
and run the exercise
one more time.
Yes, sir. 16 times now, sir.
The next one will
be 17, won't it?
Yes, sir.
Launch the tanker.
All units, Galactica.
Recover drones and prepare to
run training mission again.
We're launching
the tanker bird.
Tanker? Once you've tanked up,
head back to position Alpha and
prepare for training run 17.
Galactica out.
What the frak
are they doing over there?
This is the Commander.
Get the Admiral on the line.
Admiral, considering
how long our pilots
have been in the air, I
suggest we recall the birds
and scrub
the training exercise.
If we can't do this
in a training scenario,
how the hell are we supposed
to pull this off
with Cylon raiders
on our asses?
Huh? Tell me! What the
frak do you want from me?
I don't know how we're supposed to do
any of this crap at half strength!
Collision!
We've had a collision!
Give me your status, Kat.
Bingo, Wally, speak to me!
I'm losing flight control!
I've got red lights
all across the board!
Kat, I'm in a wild spin! I'm losing hydraulics.
My wing is going.
Galactica, Kat.
I'm declaring an emergency.
Request priority landing
for two bent birds.
Pull them in! Yes, sir.
Roger that, Kat. Bring
your birds back home.
Further instructions to follow.
This whole thing
is frakking insane.
We've got two ships
at half strength.
We've got crews that haven't seen
action in a year and a half,
and you're acting like the only problem
is they're not working hard enough?
Have you taken a look at
yourself in the mirror lately?
You're weak, soft,
mentally and physically.
This isn't about me.
You've had four months
to get your act together.
And so far all you've
been able to frakking do
is to complain and whine
about how hard it is.
Well, guess what?
It's gonna get a lot harder.
Do you understand me?
Now, I want you to turn around and
get your fat ass out of here.
Get your men ready,
or I'll find someone who can.
Dismissed!
Good shot, Anders.
Go ahead and set it up.
Move inside! Give
me the ball, right here!
I don't like this one, Colonel.
I think we're the ones
crossing the line here.
It's the only way it's gonna work.
The kid's got access and clearance.
We've got to be square on this. You
can't back out once you've started.
I'm not backing out.
It's wrong, Colonel.
You know that, don't you?
He's a soldier, Chief.
It's not the first time we've sent
a soldier on a one-way mission.
You know that, don't you?
This is different.
This is our best chance
to take out Gaius Baltar.
It may be the only one, and we're
sure as frak gonna take it.
Ever since they killed Nora,
I've got nothing to live for.
Let's go, set it up.
Now look me in the eye and you tell
me that you are committed to this.
I'm committed.
May the Gods be with you.
Some things you
just don't do, Colonel,
not even in war.
Well, maybe you'll feel different
when you're sitting in detention.
Duck volunteered. He's going.
It's a hard thing to say,
but it seems like I don't
know who my son is anymore.
The same goes
for the crew, the ship.
I feel pretty much alone.
Except maybe for you.
I wish I could come back a year
and tell that Admiral Adama
about this conversation.
A year's a long time.
Can I ask you something
very personal?
Do you feel guilty about leaving
the people behind on New Caprica?
I don't do guilt.
You know, a year ago,
when you put me in this cell,
I was at a crossroads.
I sat in here for weeks,
just consumed with rage
at all the things
that had happened to me.
And at some point I realized
it was all just guilt.
I was angry at myself for
the choices I had made.
Betraying my people,
losing my baby-
So I had a choice.
I could either move forward
or stay in the past.
But the only way to move
forward was to forgive myself.
You know, I don't
think we can survive,
I don't think the Fleet or Galactica or
the people on New Caprica can survive
unless the man at the top finds
a way to forgive himself.
Two of our pilots
almost get killed
because they've been in
the cockpit for 11 hours,
and he wants to bust my balls.
"You're soft."
Can you believe that?
What?
Oh, you agree, is that it?
Forget it.
I'm not looking for a fight.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Don't do that.
You got something to say,
come out and say it.
He's right, you are soft.
I'm not talking
about the weight.
You've lost your edge,
your confidence.
You lost your war, Lee.
And the truth is, you're
a soldier who needs a war.
And you don't want to hear it
because you've got it in your head
that your father's the soldier,
and you sure don't want
to be like him.
But you are like him.
You're more like him
than you know.
That's one of the reasons
I married you.
Okay, it's working, I think.
Is it working or isn't it?
They keep jamming us.
So much for our source
on the inside.
Ten minutes left. And lots of
nothing on the wireless as usual.
Keep an eye out for Raiders.
The last listening bird almost
got popped by a pair yesterday.
I've almost got it.
Oh, frak. Turn that thing down.
It's working. It's working.
Time's up. Spin up the
FTL, and get ready to go.
Hold on. I'm picking
something up.
It's a Colonial transmission.
It's a low power signal, but
the recognition codes match.
Oh, yeah, we've got
a link to the ground.
Okay, send the coded response,
spin up the drive,
and let's get the hell
back to Galactica.
We've got a signal.
The Raptor just
made contact with us.
What's it say?
"Will make contact this
frequency every twelve hours."
"Prepare sitrep for command authority.
Have hope. We're coming for you."
We made contact! I say
again, we made contact with the ground.
Colonel Tigh has formed an insurgent
group against the Cylons,
and now they're
ready and waiting
for instructions on how to
coordinate the rescue effort.
It's gonna be okay.
It's really gonna be okay.
These are the surveillance
pictures taken by the insurgents.
I think we can match names
to about 50 of these photos,
but our best guess puts the total
police force at around 200.
Two hundred.
I wouldn't have believed
there'd be 20 people
who would turn
against their own kind.
I want those names. I want
the rest of the names.
That's tough. The Cylons are afraid the
population will go after any human
who joins
the New Caprica Police.
As well they should.
I know I haven't lived
a model life.
I made a lot of mistakes.
I'm gonna need
your protection today.
Mr. President?
Good morning, Gaeta.
It's time for
the graduation ceremony.
Oh, yes, the ceremony.
About the ceremony.
There's been a change of plan.
I won't be going.
Security concern.
Don't look so worried.
There'll be other graduations.
Right. Okay. I'll just
let the staff know.
I think we should
call off the strike.
There's no reason to go forward if
the Galactica's gonna come back.
What, pass up a golden opportunity
to kill Gaius Baltar?
Other than that, Colonel,
I fail to see the point.
Think with your head, Chief,
not with your heart.
The only way they stand a chance
of getting us off this rock
is if the Cylons are
too distracted battling
a full-blown uprising
when they get here.
All right. If your source on the inside
says Baltar's not gonna be there, abort.
Otherwise, stick with the plan.
Hormonal
imbalances or neurological disorders.
But many have found relief at
the New Caprica medical center
where a crack team of human
and Cylon physicians...
Hey, Duck.
Fall in!
Good morning and welcome
to all graduates.
You are the hope.
You are the dream of a new tomorrow
for humans and Cylon alike.
And I salute you for the risks that you
have taken for just showing up today.
Today you begin a new career
and a new life as
provisional police officers.
And looking out
across this room,
I see the significance of this
new path is not lost on you.
Congratulations.
It's good to have you with us.
Congratulations, Sergeant.
A dangerous mission.
Congratulations, Captain. It's
great to have you with us.
I'll see you soon, Nora.